<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meta | Jake Goulding]]></title>
  <link href="http://jakegoulding.com/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jakegoulding.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-16T20:50:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jakegoulding.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Goulding]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Posterous?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jakegoulding.com/blog/2011/01/02/why-posterous/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-02T12:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jakegoulding.com/blog/2011/01/02/why-posterous</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I need something to start a blog with, why not start with why I
chose Posterous?</p>

<p>Over the Christmas holidays, I've been reading through back entries in
<a href="http://michaelfeathers.typepad.com/">Michael Feather's blog</a>. Reading through his posts (among many
other blogs) was one of the reasons I thought to start a blog, so I
figured I could start there.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Michael uses <a href="http://www.typepad.com/">Typepad</a>, but the basic blog there costs money (there
is a <a href="http://www.typepad.com/micro/">Micro service</a>, but why restrict myself?). I'm not sure that
blogging is my thing, so I didn't want to put my money where my mouth
is, so to speak.</p>

<p>Next, I checked out <a href="http://www.tumblr.com/">Tumblr</a>. Tumblr is an interesting case, as I
know the lead developer there, <a href="http://www.marco.org/">Marco Arment</a>. Not that knowing him
would really affect the quality of my blogging experience, but it's one
of those little things one can use to namedrop. The landing page for
Tumblr is amazingly clean and inviting, but what really threw me was the
<strong>URL</strong> field. I wasn't sure exactly what was supposed to
go there, so I clicked though to the <strong>Help</strong> page.</p>

<div class="image_with_caption">
   <img src="http://jakegoulding.com/images/blog/tumblr-signup.png" alt="Tumblr signup" />
   <span>Tumblr signup - simple but ultimately confusing.</span>
</div>


<p>At least that's what I would have done, but I didn't see one. <strong>About
Tumblr</strong> was the closest, so I tried that. While I was looking around, I
got distracted and wanted to know how I could export my data from
Tumblr, should the need arise. I was a little worried about the safety
of my posts, as the recent Tumblr outages have been very prominent. Not
like I expect the loss of my blog to be important, but I hate losing
anything. During my search interlude, Carol pointed out a tweet from
today about another Tumblr outage, so that seemed like a sign.</p>

<p>Conveniently, I did find a <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/09/18/stuff-white-person-doesnt-like/">post on TechCrunch</a> about switching to
Tumblr. Reading that article pointed me towards towards Posterous, which
had the ring of "all the cool kids are doing it", which is music to my
ears. The signup was almost as clean as Tumblr's, but most importantly,
it had immediate feedback for each field. In the <strong>URL</strong> field, for
example, it clearly showed that it was asking for the <em>subdomain</em> of my
future blog. Clicking on the field even shows if that domain is
available, as you type. Good UX for the win!</p>

<div class="image_with_caption">
   <img src="http://jakegoulding.com/images/blog/posterous-signup.png" alt="Posterous signup" />
   <span>Posterous signup - still simple, but a bit more useful. The URL field clearly shows you are creating a subdomain.</span>
</div>




<div class="image_with_caption">
   <img src="http://jakegoulding.com/images/blog/posterous-signup-detail.png" alt="Posterous signup detail" />
   <span>Once you've clicked on a field, you are provided with more information.</span>
</div>


<p>Reading through the help also indicated that the site operators have
their shit together, so I went for it. I didn't even think about
checking to see if I would be able to get my data back out (I did just
now, and they say you can <a href="http://help.posterous.com/can-i-export-my-site">use the API to export your data</a>).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
