<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: TPCP | Jake Goulding]]></title>
  <link href="http://jakegoulding.com/blog/categories/tpcp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jakegoulding.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-16T20:40:31-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jakegoulding.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Goulding]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Psychology of Computer Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://jakegoulding.com/blog/2011/02/05/the-psychology-of-computer-programming/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-05T12:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jakegoulding.com/blog/2011/02/05/the-psychology-of-computer-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over New Year's break, we visited one of Carol's friends in New
Orleans. While we did quite a lot of touristy things (the French
Quarter is very exciting when the new year rolls around), we also got
to visit the lovely used bookstore <strong>Beckham's Book
Shop</strong>. Unfortunately, we got there late in the day and I didn't
realize that there was an entire second floor until very near closing
time. I'm glad I took the time to look upstairs, as that is where I
discovered <a href="http://www.geraldmweinberg.com/Site/Programming_Psychology.html"><em>The Psychology of Computer Programming</em></a> by Gerald
M. Weinberg.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I grabbed the book from the shelf and glanced at the copyright date -
1971. I figured that any insights from that long ago would be
hilarious, to say the very least, so I purchased it. Upon returning
home for the evening, I was finally able to crack it open and read a
bit. Put simply, I was floored - an amazing amount of issues that were
identified <em>40 years</em> ago are still problems today.</p>

<p>When we made our way back to Pittsburgh, we had to leave our new books
behind to be shipped separately as they wouldn't fit in our
luggage. We finally got our package on Friday, and today I've been
darting in and out of chapters trying to get a feel for the
book. Every few pages I chuckle to myself (the laughter of programmers
is itself addressed in the book) and every blurb I've read aloud has
caused Carol to nod or sigh in agreement, as the case warrants.</p>

<p>My goal is to read through the book and blog about just how things
have or haven't changed and see how my experiences relate to those of
programmers from 40 years ago. One positive thing that has already
happened is that I've found out about <a href="http://bensimo.qualityfrog.com/">Ben Simo</a>, who regularly
tweets about programming papers from the 70's, both good and bad.</p>

<hr />

<p>The book itself is still available to purchase in a 25th anniversary
edition, which contains a new forward and per-chapter reflections by
the author. Maybe I will buy the updated version when I have made my
way through this edition and see how the two commentaries compare.</p>

<p>Beckham's doesn't seem to have a website, so I'll just point out thier
address and phone number in case anyone is interested.</p>

<p>Beckham's Book Shop<br/>
228 Decatur St<br/>
New Orleans, LA 70130<br/>
(504) 522-9875</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
